Register of the Edvardas Turauskas Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Edvardas Turauskas Papers
1934-1963
75015
Hoover Institution Archives
10 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope (4 linear feet)
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, printed matter, clippings, and photographs, relating to the Soviet occupation of Lithuania, 1940-1941, and Lithuanian foreign relations in Europe, 1934-1941. Also available on microfilm (14 reels).
Turauskas, Edvardas, 1896-1966
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1975.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Edvardas Turauskas, 1896-1966
1896, October 30 Born, Adriejavas, Lithuania
1918 Elected member of the First Committee of Catholic Action
1919 Entered the service of the Press Office of the Prime Minister
1919 Member of the Lithuanian Diplomatic Mission to Berne
1921 Secretary of the Lithuanian Legation in Berne
1922-23 Chargé d'Affaires of the Lithuanian Legation in Berne
1926 LL. D., University of Paris (grant from the Lithuanian Ministry of Foreign Affairs)
1926 Elected member to the Lithuanian Judicial Commission and Ministry of Foreign Affairs
1926-28 Editor-in-chief of the Catholic Lithuanian magazine Rytas
1926-1934 President of the Lithuanian-French Society in Kaunas
1928 Author, Chretienneté et Nationalité
1928-1934 Director of the section specializing in foreign affairs of the Lithuanian Telegraph Agency Elta
1929 Author, Les Fondements du Droit
1932 Author, Buts et Structure de la S. D. N.
1933 Author, Agences Telegraphiques et Bureaux de Presse
1934-39 Minister Plenipotentiary and Envoy Extraordinary of Lithuania to Prague, Belgrade, and Bucharest
1935 Author, Souveraineté de l'Eglise et de l'Etat
1939-1940 Political Director of the Lithuanian Ministry of Foreign Affairs
1940 Founding member of the Catholic Lithuanian daily magazine Zydinis
1940-46 Permanent Lithuanian Delegate to the League of Nations
1945 Author, Le Sort des Pays Baltes
1945-46 Plenipotentiary for Switzerland of the Lithuanian Relief Fund of America
Alternate Forms Available
Also available on microfilm (14 reels)
Lithuania. Uzsieniu reikalu ministerija.; Smeton, Antanas, 1874-1944.; Czechoslovakia--Foreign relations--Lithuania.; Czechoslovakia.; Diplomats--Lithuania.; Latvia--Foreign relations--Lithuania.; Latvia.; Lithuania--Foreign relations--Czechoslovakia.; Lithuania--Foreign relations--Latvia.; Lithuania--Foreign relations--Romania.; Lithuania--Foreign relations--Yugoslavia.; Lithuania--History--Soviet occupation, 1940-1941.; Lithuania.; Romania--Foreign relations--Lithuania.; Romania.; Soviet Union.; World War, 1939-1945--Lithuania.; World War, 1939-1945.; Yugoslavia--Foreign relations--Lithuania.; Yugoslavia.
- Correspondence, 1939-1946, 1956-1963 (Box 1-3)
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Ambrazevicius, J., 1941 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Ancevicius, Pranas, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Backis, S. A., 1940-1944 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Balickas, V., 1941-1943 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Balutis, B. K., 1941-1943 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Bardony, M. L. de, 1941 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Bardossy, Laszlo de, 1941 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Barsanti, Arnaldo, 1942 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Beleckas, P. J., 1940-1942 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Beuve-Mery, 1940 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Bilmanis, Alfred, 1941 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Brazenas, Nijole, 1956-1963 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - Bucys, Petras, 1940-1944 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - Budrys, Jonas, 1940-1942 (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Butenas, J., 1942 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Carnecki, Mrs., 1941 (Box-folder 1: 16)
  - Deksinys, A., 1940-1941 (Box-folder 1: 17)
  - Draugas (Chicago), 1941 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  - Dymsa, L., 1938-1939 (Box-folder 1: 19)
  - Ehret, Joseph, 1941 (Box-folder 1: 20)
  - Galvanauskas, Ernest, 1941 (Box-folder 1: 21)
  - Garbaciauskas, S., 1940-1941 (Box-folder 1: 22)
  - Girdvainis, Sutinkam, 1941-1942 (Box-folder 1: 23)
  - Grauzinis, K., 1940-1942 (Box-folder 1: 24)
  - Grinius, K., 1940-1941 (Box-folder 1: 25)
  - Grosvald, O., 1940 (Box-folder 1: 26)
  - Gylys, V., 1940-1944 (Box-folder 1: 27)
  - Husum, Carl A., 1941 (Box-folder 1: 28)
  - Journal de Genève, 1940 (Box-folder 1: 29)
  - Jurkunas, J., 1941 (Box-folder 1: 30)
  - Karvelis, P., 1941 (Box-folder 1: 31)
  - Kelistis, P., 1944 (Box-folder 1: 32)
  - Klimas, Petras, 1940-1944 (Box-folder 2: 1-3)
  - Lauckas, J. B., 1942 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Lester, Sean, 1942 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Lingis, J., 1940-1941 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Lithuanian Legation in Washington, D. C., 1940-1941 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Liutkiene, Ponia, 1942 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Liutkus, P., 1941 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Lozoraitis, S., 1941-1942 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - Matulaitis, K. A., 1941-1942 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Mikulskis, J., 1942 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Montagne, Madame de la, 1940 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Motiejunas-Valevicius, Jonas, 1942 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - Navickas, J., 1940 (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - Oeller, Ragnar, 1941 (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - Pakstas, Kazys, 1940-1944 (Box-folder 2: 17-18)
  - Panstas, Professor, 1940 (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - Prunskis, J., 1941 (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - Rabinavicius, Henrikas, 1940-1941 (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - Radvila, Princesse, 1942-1943 (Box-folder 2: 22)
  - Red Cross, International, 1941, 1943-1946 (Box-folder 2: 23)
  - Reklaitis, K., 1942 (Box-folder 2: 24)
  - Rigelis, K., 1940 (Box-folder 2: 25)
  - Saulys, Jurgis, 1942 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Saulys, Jurgis, 1942-1944 (Box-folder 3: 2-3)
  - Savickis, Jurgis, 1940-1942 (Box-folder 3: 4-5)
  - Schildt, Heinrich, 1942 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Seghers, Pierre, 1941 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Senkus, J., 1942 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Simuciui, L., 1941 (Box-folder 3: 9)
  - Simutis, A., 1941-1942 (Box-folder 3: 10)
  - Skipitis, R., 1941-1944 (Box-folder 3: 11)
  - Skirpa, Kazys, 1939-1943 (Box-folder 3: 12-14)
  - Smetona, Antanas, 1941 (Box-folder 3: 15)
  - Stonciute, Aniceta, 1941 (Box-folder 3: 16)
  - Svagzdziui, J. M., 1942 (Box-folder 3: 17)
  - Talmantui, Jurgiui, 1941 (Box-folder 3: 18)
  - Vaciulaitis, A., 1940-1942 (Box-folder 3: 19-20)
  - Vaitkevicius, J., 1942 (Box-folder 3: 21)
  - Valiukenas, A., 1942-1943 (Box-folder 3: 22-23)
  - Vokictaiciui, A., 1944 (Box-folder 3: 24)
  - Ylai, S., 1940-1941 (Box-folder 3: 25)
  - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 3: 26)
- Subject File, 1934-1951 (Box 3-9)
  Correspondence, memoranda, reports, minutes of meetings, lists, charts, notes, printed matter, and clippings, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Ancewicz, Francizek, Stalin's State Theory on the Basis of Development of the USSR (in Polish), 1939 (Box-folder 3: 27)
  - Baltic States conferences, 1938-1940 (Box-folder 3: 28)
  - Bolshevism and Imperialism (in Lithuanian), undated (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - History's Forger - A Historical Rectification (in German), undated (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Klimas, P., Lithuanian National History (in Lithuanian), undated (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - Konce, A., report on repatriated Lithuanians (in Lithuanian), 1941 (Box-folder 4: 4)
  - League of Nations, liquidation of, 1946 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Lithuania
    - Memorandum on the sovietization of Lithuania, first stage (in Lithuanian), October 1939 - October 1940 (Box-folder 4: 6)
    - Soviet occupation of, 1939-1940
      - General, 1939-1940 (Box-folder 4: 7)
      - List of Lithuanians arrested or deported, 1939-1940 (Box-folder 4: 8)
      - Societ occupation of, 1940 (Box-folder 4: 9)
      - Soviet occupation of, 1941-1944 (Box-folder 4: 10-11)
    - Vilnius territory dispute, 1939-1940 (Box-folder 4: 12)
    - Vilnius territory dispute, 1939-1940 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - World War II, undated (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - Lithuanian Activists Front, undated (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - Lithuanian Bolshevism (in Lithuanian), undated (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - Lithuanian Committee of Liberation, (VLIK - Vyriausias Lietuvos Islaisvinimo Komitetas), 1944-1951 (Box-folder 5: 5)
  - Lithuanian Consulate in Klaipeda, Bulletin, No. 9, November 16, 1939 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - Lithuanian diplomats meetings in Berne, 1940-1943 (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - Lithuanian diplomats meetings in Rome, 1940 (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - Lithuanian Legation in Czechoslovakia (Prague)
    - Correspondence, memoranda, reports, etc., 1934 (Box-folder 5: 9)
    - Correspondence, memoranda, reports, etc., 1935 (Box-folder 5: 10-11)
    - Correspondence, memoranda, reports, etc., 1936-1937 (Box-folder 5: 12)
    - Correspondence, memoranda, reports, etc., 1937-1938 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Lithuanian Legation in Germany (Berlin)
    - Correspondence, memoranda, reports, etc., 1939 (Box-folder 6: 2-3)
    - Correspondence, memoranda, reports, etc., 1940 (Box-folder 6: 4-5)
    - Correspondence with the Lithuanian Foreign Office in Kaunas regarding the Jewish population in newly detached provinces, formerly Poland, October 1939 - March 1940 (Box-folder 6: 6)
    - Memorandum on postwar Russian emigration (in Lithuanian), 1937 (Box-folder 6: 7)
    - Telegrams, 1939-1940 (Box-folder 6: 8)
  - Lithuanian Legation in Italy (Rome)
    - General, 1940-1941 (Box-folder 6: 9)
  - Lithuanian Legation in Latvia
    - Correspondence, memoranda, reports, etc., 1940 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - Lithuanian Legations in Berlin, Berne, and Rome (bound)
    - Correspondence, memoranda, reports, etc., June 1940 - December 1945 (Box-folder 7: 2)
  - Lithuanian Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Kaunas)
    - Correspondence, memoranda, reports, etc., 1937-1938 (Box-folder 7: 3-4)
    - Correspondence, memoranda, reports, etc., 1938-1940 (Box-folder 7: 5-7)
  - Lithuanian Political Situation (in German), undated (Box-folder 7: 8)
  - Lithuanian State Security Department, Bulletins, November 1939 - June 1940 (Box-folder 7: 9)
  - Moscow Intrigue - Lithuanian-USSR Relations (in Lithuanian), 1941 (Box-folder 7: 10)
  - Polish-Lithuanian relations, 1940-1943 (Box-folder 8: 1-2)
  - Radvila, Princesse
    - Library materials (Box-folder 8: 3)
    - Passport (Box-folder 8: 4)
    - Reminiscences dictated by Princesse Radvila (in French), 1941-1942 (Box-folder 8: 5)
    - Will, 1943 (Box-folder 8: 6)
  - Recollections of the Lithuanian interpreter in the Soviet occupied zone of Berlin, deported to the USSR (in Lithuanian), May 1952 - January 1953 (Box-folder 8: 7)
  - Skirpa, Kazys
    - Memorandum regarding past and possible future Latvias (in German), April 1941 (Box-folder 8: 8)
    - Memorandum regarding the reinstatement of Lithuania's national autonomy (in German), May 1941 (Box-folder 8: 9)
  - Smetona, Antanas
    - Recollections of the first days of Lithuanian political emigres in Germany and Switzerland (in Lithuanian), July - December 1940 (Box-folder 8: 10)
    - General, 1939 (Box-folder 8: 11)
    - Resignation from the post of President of Lithuania in July 1940, May - December 1940 (Box-folder 8: 12)
  - Soviet Russia Occupation of Lithuania (in Lithuanian), undated (Box-folder 8: 13)
  - Suduvis, N. E., On That Side of the Iron Curtain - Lithuania (in Lithuanian), 1946 (Box-folder 8: 14)
  - Voldemars, Augustinas, The Catholic Church in the Province of Vilna (in French), April/May 1940 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - World War II, press excerpts, 1939-1944 (Box-folder 9: 2)
- Speeches and Writings, 1939-1940, 1955-1958 (Box 9-10)
  Articles, handwritten and typewritten manuscripts, and lectures, by Edvardas Turauskas, arranged alphabetically by title or subject.
  - Articles written for Lithuanian magazines, Zidinys and Politika (in Lithuanian), 1934-1940 (Box-folder 9: 3)
  - Letters to the Communist Brothers (in Lithuanian), March - December 1958 (Box-folder 9: 4)
  - Voice of America, manuscripts and drafts for, 1955-1958 (Box-folder 10: 1-2, Box-folder 9: 5-6)
- Increment, July 1986 (Box 10)
  - Typewritten diary, 1956-1958 (Box-folder 10: 3)
- Photographs
  - 42 prints / 1 envelope. 40 photographs depicting atrocities committed by Soviet forces in Lithuania. Included are 2 photographs of Aniceta Stoucinte., June-July 1941 (Photo file Envelope A)